Guide to the Daniel M. Tredwell papers ARC.188
Brooklyn Historical Society
Daniel M. Tredwell papers
1876-1917
ARC.188
Brooklyn Historical Society
1.5 Linear feet in four manuscript boxes.
The Daniel M. Tredwell papers contain manuscripts of histories, essays, lectures, and reminiscences by Daniel Melancthon Tredwell (1826-1921). Dating from circa 1870s through circa 1910s, these manuscript writings primarily concern Long Island, especially Kings, Nassau, and Suffolk counties, with the towns of Flatbush and Hempstead appearing most frequently. The collection includes three major manuscripts, one on Kings County history, another on Native Americans of Long Island, and the last dating from circa 1888 concerning Tredwell's personal reminiscences of nineteenth century Long Island. There are also many shorter pieces on history, ethnography, philosophy, and other matters of intellectual inquiry. Topics of local historical interest include Melrose Hall in Flatbush, the organization of the Brooklyn Philosophical Society, and a history of the Apprentices Library Association. Other writings range from women's rights to metaphysics to biographical notes.
Tredwell, Daniel M., (Daniel Melancthon), 1826-1921
Biographical note
Daniel Melancthon Tredwell (1826-1921) was a lawyer, Chief Clerk of the Supreme Court of Brooklyn, officer of the Home Title Insurance Company of Brooklyn and, most relevant for this collection, author of local histories concerning Brooklyn and Long Island. He was born near Freeport, L.I. and died in Brooklyn. He was a member of the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society), the Kings County Historical Society and the American Ethnological Society, among other organizations. (Source: New York Times obituary, November 12, 1921.)
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The source of the three major manuscripts and the smaller set of essays is unknown, but quite possibly came from Tredwell himself, a member of the Long Island Historical Society (now Brooklyn Historical Society), or through the Society's acquisition of the records of the Kings County Historical Society. The bulk of the essays (accession 1974.071) were purchased from G.A. Baker and Co. in 1938.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged in order of the five accessions that comprise it. The three major manuscripts appear first, followed by two sets of shorter pieces. Each of these two sets is arranged by topic, moving from specific matters of local history to those concerning broader subjects, each set closing with a folder of miscellaneous writings, clippings, and fragments. There is some overlap in topics and multiple versions of material across the accessions.
Scope and Contents
The Daniel M. Tredwell papers contain manuscripts of histories, essays, lectures, reminiscences, and notes by Daniel Melancthon Tredwell (1826-1921). These primarily concern Long Island, especially Kings, Nassau (formerly part of Queens), and Suffolk counties, with the towns of Flatbush and Hempstead appearing most frequently. The collection includes three major manuscripts. One of these concerns Kings County's history and includes discussion of topography and its development from the mid-nineteenth to early twentieth centuries; Indians and Dutch, including their traditions, cultures, agriculture, and influence; and the American Revolution. Native Americans of Long Island are also a subject of a second major manuscript. A third manuscript of personal reminiscences dating from circa 1888 is based on a journal maintained by Tredwell for over 50 years, beginning in 1838. This manuscript progresses in roughly chronological order until early 1845, with personal reflections on Indian relics, meteor showers, the destruction of an old oak tree during a storm, his visit to a Millerite encampment near Hempstead, riding the Long Island Railroad, the Amistad affair, sheep herding and parting, and marshing, among other topics.
In addition to the three major manuscripts, there are many shorter pieces on history, ethnography, philosophy, and other matters of intellectual interest. Topics of local historical interest include pieces on Melrose Hall in Flatbush, the organization of the Brooklyn Philosophical Society, and a history of the Apprentices Library Association. The subjects of other writings range from women's rights to metaphysics to biographical notes on Gabriel Harrison (actor, photographer, and artist; 1818-1902) and Gilbert Vale (writer; 1788-1866).
Tredwell's writings, especially his histories and reminiscences, seem to be a product of his own recollections, "rambles," inquiries, and readings. Most of the material is undated but appears to range from the 1870s to 1910s. Accordingly, the writings often combine first-hand observations of mid-nineteenth century Long Island, with commentary on developments in the later part of the century, with attempts to understand the history of Long Island in a broader intellectual context.
Related Materials
The Davenport family papers (call number 1977.345) held by Brooklyn Historical Society includes some correspondence (1877-1893) to Tredwell. BHS also has some material authored by Tredwell on the library shelves. These can be found by searching the on-line catalog, Bobcat.
Brooklyn Apprentices' Library Association.; Melrose Hall (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Tredwell, Daniel M., (Daniel Melancthon), 1826-1921; Biographies; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs |y 19th century; Essays; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.) |x History; Hempstead (N.Y.) |x History; Histories; Indians of North America |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Indians of North America |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Kings County (N.Y.) |x History |y 19th century; Lecture notes; Long Island (N.Y.) |x History; Notes; Reminiscences; Suffolk County (N.Y.) |X History
- "Kings County in Fact, Legend and Tradition" manuscript and early paper (2 items), 1886, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "An Account of Indians of Long Island: Historical and Ethnological", circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 1-12)
- "Personal Reminiscences of Men and Things on Long Island" (1 of 2), circa 1888 (Box 2, Folder 13-20)
- "Personal Reminiscences of Men and Things on Long Island" (2 of 2), circa 1888 (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
- "Freeport"; "Montauk"; "Whaling", circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- "An Early Paper on Indians", circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- "Legends-Ghost", circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Paerdegat Creek; Streams of Hempstead, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
- "How I Won My Spurs", 1913 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  General note
  Includes personal reminiscences of 1840s-1850s Brooklyn Heights.
- "Overheard"; "Move Up!!", circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Includes reflections on Long Island real estate development.
- "Ethnological, Pillars of Hercules, Pacific Ocean", circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous Papers, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- "When We Came To Flatbush Thirty Five Years Ago", circa 1879 (Box 3, Folder 18, 19)
- "The Flatbush People", circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- "Melrose Hall, With Some Account of Its Tenants", circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- "The Organization of the Brooklyn Philosophical Society", 1879 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- "The History of the Apprentices Library Association", 1913 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- "How I Won My Spurs," or "Assault on Fulton Street", circa 1913 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
- "Freeport", circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- "Fire Island", circa 1914 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- "Marshes", circa 1888 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- "Long Island's Oldest Inhabitant [Horse-Foot Crab]", circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- "A Conversation on the Long Island Railroad", circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Woman's Work, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Woman's Rights, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Toys and Games, circa 1890 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Early Explorers of America, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- "Central America", circa 1880 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- "Myths" [Mythology], 1876 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Gilbert Vale, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- "A Short Essay on Mines and Minerals", circa 1910 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- "Sketch of Gabriel Harrison", 1913 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- "Spontaneity" [Spontaneous Generation of Life], circa 1877 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- "Are We Immortal?", 1879 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- "Metaphysical", circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Miscellaneous Papers, circa 1900 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Correspondence: Akerly to Tredwell, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 23)